[film reel whirring]
[intriguing music]
[tools whirring]
[Narrator] In October 2018,
the anonymous street artist
known as Banksy published
this video online.
In it, he can be seen
preparing a custom frame
for his painting,
Girl with Balloon.
The painting is about to be
offered for sale at Sotheby's,
one of the world's most
exclusive auction houses.
[dramatic music]
I have $30,000 dollars.
Have we got 32,000?
The event was a
typical art auction.
Banksy's lot was the
last lot of the evening.
The piece sold for
over a million US.
Last chance at 850,000 pounds.
The gavel came down,
sold, gone, sold.
Selling for 860,000.
[bangs gavel]
As the hammer struck,
the work started to
fall through the frame.
-[commotion]
-[beeping]
And as it did, it shredded.
And everybody witnessed in
horror as it was destroyed.
I was like [inaudible]
[grunts]
Street artist Banksy pulled off
one of the greatest pranks in
the history of the art world.
It caused a huge stir.
I mean, nothing like
that had ever happened.
[speaking in foreign language]
That stunt has already
increased the value
of that painting
up to $7 million.
It plays on people's
fears and emotions
and what true value is.
Where do we place
value in society?
Who does art belong to?
He created an art history moment
and wrote himself again
into the history books.
[rock music]
[curious music]
[Narrator] The stunt atSotheby's wasn't the first time
that Banksy had ambushed
one of the august
institutions of the art world.
15 years earlier, in
the winter of 2003,
a mysterious figure
entered Tate Britain,
one of the UK's most
prestigious art museums
and placed a
painting on the wall.
Over the following 18 months,
fake exhibits appeared
in London's Natural History
Museum, the Louvre in Paris,
and the Museum of
Modern Art in New York,
all covertly installed by
the same anonymous stranger.
He went through seven
different galleries,
putting seven different works
of art up in these galleries.
The one in the
Metropolitan Museum of Art
only lasted two hours,
which was understandable,
because it was a painting of
a rather posh-looking lady.
She had a gas mask on, and
that was spotted very quickly.
But the one in
the Museum of Art,
that lasted for several days,
because it was a painting
of a Tesco can of soup,
and it looked just like
the Warhol cans of soup,
and no one noticed it.
It was a daring thing to do.
He did it, he got away with it,
and everyone suddenly
knew his name.
[Narrator] But a name
was all the public had.
Everything else
remained a mystery.
Who was the secretive
artist that had evaded
some of the world's
tightest security
to hang his own work
alongside that of Monet,
Picasso, and Warhol?
Was he just one person?
Or was Banksy a group of people?
Was he hiding his identity
because he was already famous,
someone known to the public,
perhaps a musician or actor?
The stunts themselves
contained clues.
Banksy had launched anaudacious game of cat and mouse.
At the Tate, he
had risked arrest
to bring his art to the public.
In the Met, his piece had been
quickly removed by curators
who were sure that it
didn't belong in a gallery.
And at Sotheby's, Banksy had
performed an act of vandalism.
And it was with vandalism
that it had all started.
[loud banging]
[energetic hip hop music]
[Voice Actor] Graffiti hasbeen used to start revolutions,
start wars, and
generally is the voice
of the people who
aren't listened to.
Graffiti is one of
the few tools you have
if you have almost nothing.
And even if you don't
come up with a picture
to cure world
poverty, you can make
someone smile when
they're having a piss.
Graffiti isn't an art form.
Graffiti is a reaction,
an impulse,
is like a spark.
Dynamic, explosive,
unpredictable.
Some people say
graffiti ruined my life
and some people say
graffiti saved my life.
A rush.
It's an addiction.
The rush, I think, is sort
of a consequence of it all.
You're scared, and
your blood is pumping,
and your adrenaline is pumping.
But really you're doing
it for the recognition
and not the rush.
Running round a city
and getting your name up
in as many places
as you possible can.
The more risky, the better.
You want your name as big
as possible in lights.
It's fucking ridiculous,
but. [chuckles]
Graffiti is always the
heartbeat of society.
It captures what's going on
at that time, in that moment.
For every Banksy that's
on top and is visible,
you've got hundreds that may
be underground and invisible.
[train clacking]
[upbeat hip hop music]
Graffiti emerged in Philadelphia
and then New York in the
late '60s and early '70s.
The city was in
quote/unquote crisis.
It was a city that
didn't have much revenue.
There was a lot of crime,
there was a lot of
drugs, a lot of poverty.
Graffiti writing
started in neighborhoods
like the Upper West Side
of Manhattan, the Bronx,
Flatbush Avenue in Brooklyn,
and it was a movement
started by young kids that
were writing their names
with their street numbers
on the walls around town
to get recognized in some way.
Sort of a game of tag.
You're actually putting
your name on a place
and sort of putting it
more and more and more
and exposing yourself more,
and then someone
else is coming in,
following you and
doing the same thing.
The game exploded
when kids decided
to leave their streets
and go to the next street
and the next street
and the next neighborhood and
the neighborhood after that.
And it became hugely popular.
The taller and wider
people sprayed their names,
then somebody came up
with the bright idea
of putting a second
color round their name.
And before you know
it, the stick letters
of small names on
the back of bus seats
had turned into
seven-foot-high letters
on the side of subway trains.
And so then it really exploded
and became an art movement.
[upbeat hip hop music]
[Narrator] Painting, or bombing,New York's subways system
soon became the primary focus
for young graffiti writers
obsessed with having their nameseen as widely as possible.
The nascent art movement
developed its own grammar,
rules, and culture,
all based around
rendering letter
forms, from the tag,
a signature scrawled quicklywith a spray can or marker pen,
all the way up to the
piece, a large-scale,
stylized depiction
of the artist's name.
In 1983, the public was
given its first glimpse
inside the graffiti
underground, with Tony Silver
and Henry Chalfant's
landmark film "Style Wars".
For many, Style Wars
depicted a strange, criminal,
and dangerous subculture.
But for others, it proved
to be an inspiration.